Okay, so today's דף daf is כ"ז, kaf zayin, but we're behind
a little bit so we start on כ"ו עמוד א' chaf vav
amud aleph near the bottom. אוכלין אכילת עראי חוץ לסוכה. ochlin achilat
arai chutz lasukkah. So we spent a lot of time yesterday in
the importance questions about a sick person and מצטער, mitzta'er, a person
in discomfort being exempt from the סוכה, sukkah, people who are traveling
being exempt, and we really looked there at the larger issue about
how you have a wide range of exemptions because the מצוה mitzvah
in its core is not just a narrow technical issue of eating
x amount in a סוכה, sukkah, it's a broader concept of fundamentally
living in a סוכה. sukkah. And because that's a broader abstract concept,
there are therefore more latitudes about what types of realities are considered
to be living or not living in a place. But we contrast
that to nowadays where we've translated the obligation into a very limited
narrow technical sense in terms of eating x amount, we've even dropped
the idea of sleeping, and therefore in that context it's a little
surprising to hear these wide ranges of exemptions. But the more it's
an all-encompassing obligation, the more those exemptions make sense. So now we
turn to this issue of eating and sleeping in a סוכה sukkah
and actually begin to sort of quantify exactly how much we're talking
about, because the משנה mishna says you could eat temporary, eat and
drink sort of temporary, not a fixed meal outside of the סוכה.
sukkah. So the גמרא gemara says the following. This is about ten
lines before the lines get wide, about fifteen lines from the bottom.
וכמה אכילת עראי, vekamah achilat arai, what's considered to be only a
temporary eating? Up to how much? אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
תרתי ותלת בי, tarti u'tlat bei, two or three eggs worth. רש"י,
Rashi, if you look, רש"י Rashi did not have the גירסא girsa
of בי bei and רש"י Rashi says תרתי ותלת, tarti u'tlat, שתים
או שלש פעמים יתן לתוך פיו shtayim o shalosh pe'amim yiten l'toch
piv
morsels. So it's nice to see that interesting French word, morsels. Anyway,
but the amount that you normally are considered to be able to
swallow in one go is an egg, so it's pretty consistent with
our גירסא girsa of two to three eggs worth. אמר רב יוסף,
amar Rav Yosef, so that's what he says. אמר ליה אביי, amar
leh Abaye, אביי Abaye says back, זימנין סגיאין סגי ליה לאינשי בהכי,
zimnin sagi'in sagi leh l'inshi bahachi, sometimes two or three eggs worth
is enough to fill people. So that would be an אכילת קבע,
achilat keva, והויא ליה סעודת קבע. v'havia leh seudat keva. אלא אמר
אביי, ella amar Abaye, rather אביי Abaye says, כדי טעימת בר בי
רב דאזיל לבי כלה, kedei te'imat bar bei rav de'azeil l'bei kallah,
like a ישיבה בחור, yeshiva bachur, you know, takes a little taste
of something before he goes in to the learning for the day,
which is not exactly clear how much it is, but it's assumed
to be the amount you could swallow in one go. So therefore
it's assumed to be one egg's worth, not two to three eggs
worth, and up to that is considered temporary. Now of what type
of a food are we talking about? Interestingly, our גמרא gemara does
not distinguish what type of food you're eating, only talks about quantity.
You know, there is a גמרא gemara that exists actually elsewhere in
יומא yoma that actually discusses the question about whether פירי, peiri, whether
fruit is בר סוכה bar sukkah or not, needs a סוכה. sukkah.
And the conclusion of that גמרא gemara is that fruit does not
need a סוכה. sukkah. The question is what's in the category of
fruit and what's in the category, even if you're going with it,
what's in the category of fruit and what's in the category of
other things. Generally it's assumed that bread and מזונות mezonos certainly is
what we're talking about here. Fruit, based on the גמרא gemara in
יומא, yoma, certainly is what we're not. How about things that are
in the middle, like meat and potatoes? Where does that go? So
there's a whole debate about which category that goes in. We tend
to be, as I've already indicated,
pretty limiting, narrow in our definition of what technically is obligated in
a סוכה sukkah and we focus on bread and מזונות, mezonos, and
wine is somewhat discussed. But that interestingly in our גמרא gemara here,
what you're eating is not discussed, just how much. And now we
are saying that according to אביי Abaye up to
an egg's worth, up to and including an egg's worth
can be outside of a
סוכה.
sukkah. תנו רבנן, tanah rabbanan, אוכלין אכילת עראי חוץ לסוכה, ochlin achilat
arai chutz lasukkah,
you can eat a temporary eating out of the סוכה, sukkah, ואין
ישנין שינת עראי חוץ לסוכה, v'ein yeshenin shenat arai chutz lasukkah, but
not a temporary sleeping, you can't take a nap. מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason why is a nap different than
eating? אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, גזירה שמא ירדם, gezeira shema
yiradem,
we're afraid that you'll fall into a deep sleep. So technically a
nap is not a problem but we're afraid of where it will
lead to. אמר ליה אביי, amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said to
him, אלא הא דתניא, ella hadatanya,
that which we learn in
a ברייתא, braisa, ישן אדם שינת עראי בתפילין, yeshan adam shenat arai
bi'tefillin, a person can have a temporary sleeping with תפילין, tefillin, אבל
לא שינת קבע, aval lo shenat keva, but not a permanent one.
So according to you, every time you allow somebody to nap, you're
afraid that it'll be a deep sleep. So how can you ever
halachically distinguish between the two? Because one will always lead into the
other.
אמר רב יוסף בריה דרב עילאי, amar Rav Yosef brei de'Rav Ilai,
במוסר שינתו לאחרים, b'moser shinato l'acherim,
alright,
that would be a case where you told other people to wake
you up, so that's a special circumstance and that's why it would
be allowed to take that nap with your תפילין tefillin on.
מתקיף לה רב משרשיא, matkif lah Rav Mesharsheya, so רב
משרשיא Rav Mesharsheya asked... Your co-signer, your guarantor, he needs his own
guarantor. How do you know the guy you've asked for won't himself
fall asleep? So this is actually interesting because this issue about can
you have somebody else remind you comes up about issues like can
you do certain things before you דאוון daven and so on, and
do we say you can't trust somebody that they'll forget? So what
about if you use electronic devices and set alarms? So that's a
very serious question. But anyway, he says it cannot be. If you're
afraid that a napping will lead to a deep sleep, then there's
no explanation of why you're allowed to take a nap with תפילין.
tefillin. So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. אלא אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן
Ella amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan במניח ראשו בין
ברכיו עסקינן. bimeniach rosho bein birkav askinan. Fine. We're not talking about
that you're trusting somebody else, but we're talking about that you're not
lying down on a couch for a little nap. Talking about you
put your head between your knees. You know, it's like trying to
fall asleep on an airplane flight. So, you know, sometimes maybe you're
lucky and it happens, but basically if you're just putting your head
between your knees, you're putting your head down on your desk, you're
not lying down, we're not afraid that that'll turn into a big
sleep. So fundamentally, there's nothing wrong with a nap, but we're always
concerned that a nap will turn into a sleep, into a deep
sleep. Why do we allow it by תפילין? tefillin? Because it's a
special case when it won't happen. רבא, Rava, אמר רבא amar Rava
says, אין קבע לשינה. ein keva lesheinah. רבא Rava says no, there's
a difference. רבא Rava says that it's about by סוכה, Sukkah, the
issue sort of what we're going to say is that by תפילין,
tefillin, the concern is not about sleeping per se. There's no problem
per se to sleep with תפילין. tefillin. The problem is passing gas.
So by תפילין, tefillin, a tiny little nap we're not afraid that
it'll happen, only when you get to a big sleep, and that's
why the whole concern by תפילין tefillin was that a nap will
turn into a sleep. But רבא Rava says, I'm not concerned that
naps will turn into a sleep. A nap is a nap. A
nap won't turn into a deep sleep. So by תפילין tefillin where
the only issue is passing gas, and that's only a concern when
you're in a deep sleep, you're allowed to nap. A nap will
just be a nap, and that's not a problem by תפילין. tefillin.
But by סוכה, Sukkah, that's different. By סוכה, Sukkah, it's not what
will happen to it, it's that the very act of taking a
nap is considered to be קבע. keva. What does that mean it's
considered to be קבע? keva? Because remember, by סוכה Sukkah the question
is what types of acts constitute living in a place? So you
know, when you're going out at other places, you know, you'll take
a little snack, right? You'll snack on the street, you'll snack in
your office, you'll snack wherever you are. Snacking is something you do,
not specifically in your house. But sleeping, it would be very rare
for you to sleep somewhere that's not your house. If you're ever
lucky enough to have a couch in your office, so maybe you
can sleep in your office too. But fundamentally, eating are types of
things that are not necessarily, especially a little snacking is something that
doesn't necessarily speak about where you live to the same degree of
the places where you will nap. And therefore he says, napping is
considered to be a, you know, central to the idea and act
that is central to the idea of living in a place, and
that's what it means אין קבע לשינה, ein keva lesheinah, you know,
or what's the phrase like אין קבע לשינה. ein keva lesheinah. But
if the concern is passing gas, there's a difference between napping and
a deep sleep. But if the center is where are you sort
of setting your roots down, there even by a nap is defined,
defines where it is that you are living. Okay, so that's a
very nice conceptual difference. תני חדא ישן אדם בתפילין שינת עראי ולא
שינת קבע. Tani chada yashen adam bitfillin sheinat arai velo sheinat keva.
Now we have three ברייתות. braisos. One ברייתא braisa says you can
sleep with תפילין tefillin temporary but not permanent. That's sort of what
we've been saying, that we're not afraid of passing gas and maybe
it's a special case according to אביי Abaye where you won't come
to or somebody or where you won't come to lead to a
deep sleep, or I'm sorry, with רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, excuse me, אבל לא שינת קבע. aval lo sheinat keva.
ותניא אידך בין קבע בין עראי, Vetanya idach bein keva bein arai,
that you're allowed to do both temporary and permanent. That's a pretty
big
surprise. ותניא אידך לא קבע ולא עראי, Vetanya idach lo keva velo
arai, you're not allowed either.
So how do you explain these three ברייתות braisos other than to
say that they're arguing? לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
דנקיט להו בידיה, Ha denakit lehu bideih, if you're holding onto תפילין
tefillin in your hands, so then you can
sleep, I'm sorry, there you can
not sleep even permanent, excuse me, אפילו עראי, afilu arai, right. That's
when it's the most strict because even a little nap your hands
will open up and your תפילין tefillin will fall down. So even
though it's not on you and there's not a passing gas issue,
if you're holding it in your hand, even a nap would be
a problem. הא דמנח ברישיה, Ha dmanach beireisheih, the second case, the
middle case, is when you're wearing it, it's on your head. It's
interesting that the גמרא Gemara often emphasizes the head תפילין tefillin when
it talks about this, like when it speaks about somebody who never
wore תפילין, tefillin, it talks about קרקפתא דלא מנח תפילין, karkafta dlo
manach tefillin, a skull that never had תפילין tefillin on it. It's
fascinating the גמרא's Gemara focus more on the תפילין של ראש tefillin
shel rosh over the תפילין של יד. tefillin shel yad. So I
don't know, maybe because it's the רוב, rov, it's visible. Anyway, so
if it's on your head, if you're wearing it, that's our distinction.
A nap is okay, we're not afraid of passing gas, deep sleep
is a problem because you'll come to pass gas. הא דפריס סודרא
עלויה, Ha defaris sudra ilaviyei, and if however it's wrapped up in
a handkerchief and you're just sort of sleeping nearby it and you're
protecting it, or Then that would be okay. Okay, what was the
חידוש? chiddush? Yeah, well maybe it's not appropriate to even be sleeping
having it in bed with you, you know, it's by your pillow,
you know, there's so that but that's okay because it's wrapped up
and it's not being worn. דכמה שינת עראי de-kama shinat arai now,
now that we've distinguished for תפילין tefillin purposes, not for סוכה sukka
for the reasons we said, but for תפילין tefillin purposes we distinguish
between a napping and a sleeping, a deep sleep, what can constitute
napping? So תני רמי בר יחזקאל tani Rami bar Yechezkel כדי הילוך
מאה אמה kedei hiluch me'ah amah the time it takes to walk
a hundred אמות. amot. Now how long is a hundred אמות? amot?
So I will tell you halachically we basically assume there's a debate
about all this but we basically assume that the time it takes
to walk a מיל mil is eighteen minutes. Okay, so that's relevant
for like the idea of when שקיעה shkiah is and צאת tzeit
well not שקיעה shkiah but צאת tzeit and all those places to
say. A מיל mil is two thousand אמות. amot. So for simplicity's
sake let's call let's call it twenty minutes not eighteen minutes. Okay,
so if two thousand אמות amot for twenty minutes, so you do
the math, if a hundred אמות amot every minute, right? Did you
get that? Right? Because two thousand אמות amot right is what is
right
is twenty times a hundred, right, so therefore it's about one minute.
So a hundred אמות amot is about one minute. What?
You take a one minute nap?
A one minute nap, right. Very temporary, really, a real power nap.
Look, I I find sometimes I can go like for five ten
minutes and it'll compensate for like two three hours of missed sleep
the night before it'll be great, but you know, that's five minutes,
that's not one minute. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says כדי
הילוך מאה אמה kedei hiluch me'ah amah which is about a minute.
תניא נמי הכי tanya nami hachi המנמנם הישן בתפילין וראה קרי ha-menamnem
ha-yashen be-tefillin ve-ra'ah keri if somebody is sleeping in תפילין tefillin and
now here's a new problem which is not doesn't seem to be
the normal concern but here it's talking about if this happens, somebody
is sleeping with תפילין tefillin and they have a seminal emission, אוחז
ברצועה ocheiz ba-retzuah you grab to the to the strap ואינו אוחז
בקציצה ve-eino ocheiz ba-ketzitzah but you don't and you have to remove
it, you shouldn't be wearing it while you're in this state before
you've cleaned yourself up, so you're told by the strap but not
by the actual like base itself, not by the actual box itself.
דברי רבי יעקב divrei Rabbi Yaakov that's what רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov
says. וחכמים אומרים ve-Chachamim omrim and the חכמים Chachamim say ישן אדם
בתפילין שינת עראי ולא שינת קבע yashen adam be-tefillin shinat arai ve-lo
shinat keva that you can sleep temporary but not permanent. It's funny,
רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov didn't relate to that question. So תוספות Tosafot
says maybe they're debating whether we allow you to take a like
to take a you know to take a nap at night, you
know, it's somehow they're debating what what types of cases were concerned
will lead to קבע keva maybe anyway, not exactly clear where רבי
יעקב Rabbi Yaakov holds about this עראי arai and קבע keva but
nevertheless דכמה שינת עראי de-kama shinat arai but within the חכמים Chachamim
that make clearly this distinction and how much is a temporary sleep?
כדי הילוך מאה אמה kedei hiluch me'ah amah a hundred אמה amah
which again is very little, it's like a minute. אמר רב amar
Rav said רב, Rav, אסור לאדם לישן ביום יותר משינת הסוס asur
le-adam lishan ba-yom yoter mi-shinat ha-sus
you can't sleep in a day, so now that before we were
talking about wearing תפילין tefillin and a concern that'll lead to a
deep sleep and passing gas, now we're just talking about, you know,
you shouldn't be wasting your time taking naps in the middle of
the day. רש״י Rashi says ביטול תורה. bittul Torah. So how you
can't sleep יותר משינת הסוס yoter mi-shinat ha-sus more than a horse's
sleep. Okay, וכמה שינת הסוס ve-kama shinat ha-sus how much does a
horse sleep? שיתין נשמי shitin nishmei sixty breaths. I don't know what
that means but I guess sixty inhales and exhales of a horse,
so I don't know, I've never worked with horses I don't know,
but that can't be too much. What is that, sixty seconds? Also
a minute? Again, very little time, one minute. אמר אביי amar Abaye
so what? Three
and a half minutes according to the שערי תשובה Shaarei Teshuvah and
the רבינו ינה Rabbeinu Yonah by the way. For
humans. There you go. For humans. So a breath of a horse
is what, five seconds? No, for human. No, three seconds or about
sixty breaths. שיתין נשמי shitin nishmei is not
clearly defined.
Not clearly defined, right.
Between the horse but the thing is the time in between the
breaths is half hour.
Oh, that's a good point.
In other words, it could be a half hour. For humans, the
average is about sixteen or so.
About how much?
Twelve to sixteen per minute.
Twelve to sixteen breaths per minute. Ah, interesting, interesting. Okay, so that's
good because it's also the time between the breaths. So if you're
saying three minutes, that's three and a half minutes, that's also about
sixteen breaths per minute. It's actually figuring about the same as it
is for humans although I don't know what it is for horses.
Alright, so it's a half hour sleep for horses. Three and a
half hours?
Half hour.
A
half hour for horses to take sixty breaths?
It could be, and then another opinion says sixty breaths in not
less than three hours.
Okay, why am I guessing that the opinions quoted there actually never
actually did any empirical studies? I'm just I'm just taking a wild
guess. Alright, it can't be too much. It sounds like three to
five minutes is probably a reasonable guess, although three's quite extreme. I
mean,
but like I said, for my power naps I need at least
ten fifteen minutes. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
אביי amar Abaye so I I פסקן pasken like the position thirty
minutes, we'll have to tell the horses, okay? So אמר אביי amar
Abaye so אביי Abaye says שינתיה דמר shinetei de-Mar the sleeping of
the master, which is רבה Rabbah which is אביי׳ס Abaye's רבי, Rebbi,
כדרב ke-de-Rav so as the way he so רבה Rabbah learned how
much to nap during the day from his רבי Rebbi רב. Rav.
ודרב ve-de-Rav and רב Rav learned it כדרבי ke-de-Rebbi slept as much
during the day like his רבי. Rebbi. which is רבי, Rebbe, רבי
יהודה הנשיא. Rebbe Yehuda HaNasi. ורבי, ve-Rebbe, and רבי Rebbe did, learned
how much to nap during the day כדוד, ke-Dovid, not like, he
had a tradition going all the way back to דוד. Dovid. ודוד,
ve-Dovid, and how long did דוד Dovid nap during the day? כסוסיא,
ke-susya, like a horse. וסוסיא שיתין נשמי, ve-susya sheetin nishmei, so that's
we're back to that. 60 breaths is the amount you should be
napping during the day. אביי הוי ניים, Abaye hava noyam, now אביי
Abaye would sleep, כדי מיעל מפומבדיתא לבי כובי, ke-de-me-al mi-Pumbedita le-Bei Kuvi,
the time it took to travel from פומבדיתא Pumbedita to בי כובי.
Bei Kuvi. Now how far is that? So if you look at
רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, מפרש במקום אחרי דהוי שיתא פרסי, me-faraish
be-makom acharei de-hava shisha parsei, it says in another place six פרסי,
parsei, and then the תוספות Tosafot say they have no idea where
it says it in this other place, and never says that this
is the distance of six פרסאות. parsaot. But a פרסה parsa is
four מיל, mil, okay? Now a מיל mil I told you is
18 minutes. So a פרסה parsa is 72 minutes. Let's even round
and call it an hour. So according to רש״י, Rashi, if it's
six פרסאות, parsaot, that's six hours! That's quite a different extreme than
what we've been talking about, okay? That is some nap. So קרי
עליה רב יוסף, kari alei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said about אביי, Abaye, who
אביי Abaye was his student, עד מתי עצל תשכב, ad masai atzel
tishkav, oh lazy person how long will you sleep? מתי תקום משנתך,
masai takum mi-shinascha, when will you get up from your slumber? So
on the one hand you have one extreme which is like one
minute, three minutes, maybe five minutes, a שיתין, sheetin, right? At that,
at that at least maybe we can manage. But according to רש״י,
Rashi, אביי Abaye went six hours. It's a little hard to imagine
and use the bathroom. Well yeah, anyway.
Yes. My question was if you're not allowed to hold the תפילין
tefillin by the straps, והיו חייך תלוים לך מנגד, ve-hayu chayecha teluyim
lecha mi-neged, that he holds it by the.
Well first of all, it could be the wraps here and it's
on. I mean also you have no choice here, you know, you
have to remove it and this is the only
way to hold it by.
That's not considered, it's not considered כבוד kavod to be holding the
body when you're in this state, but why, you know, to have
directly be in contact with the actual בית bayis of the תפילין.
tefillin. But I hear, the point is true. Under normal circumstances you
don't hold it by the straps. Alright, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, הנכנס
לישן ביום, ha-nichnas lishon ba-yom, if somebody goes to sleep during the
day, you want to take a nap during the day, and we
just talked about only a temporary nap, not a permanent nap, so
not a deep sleep, so during the day presumably it would only
be a nap, so that we learned was possibly okay. So that's
why it says רצה חולץ רצה מניח, ratza choletz ratza meniach, if
you want you could take it off, if you want you could
leave it
on. בלילה, Ba-layla, if you're going at night, חולץ ואינו מניח, choletz
ve-eino meniach, you have to take it off and you can't leave
it on because that's about an issue about a deep sleep or
even maybe a nap at night might lead to a deep sleep.
We haven't discussed that but תוספות Tosafot discusses whether napping and the
concern of napping leading to a deep sleep would be different in
the day or at night. דברי רבי נתן, Divrei Rabbi Nosson, that's
what רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson said. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, הילדים, ha-yeladim, which is so funny הילדים
ha-yeladim we translate as kids but here it means young men, לעולם
חולצים ואינם מניחים, le-olam chaltzim ve-einam menichim, they always have to take
off their תפילין tefillin and can't leave them on, presumably even during
the daytime, מפני שרגילים בטומאה, mipnei she-ragilim be-tumah, because they are constantly
they have a more accustomed for טומאה, tumah, which means that they
will more regularly have seminal emission. So we think it just means
that they'll more naturally when they sleep, until now we've been talking
about a concern of passing gas, but
maybe הילדים ha-yeladim even means, you know, teenagers even before they're married,
you know, people we're afraid that they'll have seminal emission when they
sleep and therefore even if they nap, it's going to be a
concern, this will be a concern.
What, you mean young men after they're married?
Well we're going to see in a minute. Right now we assume
even if they're not married. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא קסבר
רבי יוסי בעל קרי אסור להניח תפילין, leima kasavar Rabbi Yossi baal
keri assur le-haniach tefillin, maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi holds that somebody
who has had a seminal emission can't wear תפילין? tefillin? Because we
know a whole discussion in ברכות Brachos is that when a person
is a בעל קרי, baal keri, are they forbidden to דאוון, daven,
to say ברכות, brachos, to do any to learn תורה Torah until
they go to the מקוה? mikvah? So maybe this is a similar
issue, he's concerned that you'll be a בעל קרי baal keri and
therefore they won't be able to wear תפילין. tefillin. Now of course
it's a little bit strange because if he was a concern about
if they were a בעל קרי baal keri when they were awake,
he wouldn't say, you know, he wouldn't say when they're going to
sleep, he would say that they cannot, you know, they can't wear
תפילין tefillin in general because they're often a בעל קרי. baal keri.
So and if the only concern is that they'll become a בעל
קרי baal keri while they're sleeping, which seems to be the issue,
then it's not the issue about being
a
בעל קרי baal keri that's
אסור בתפילין. assur be-tefillin. בעל קרי Baal keri means something that happened
before. Like here the concern is while you're wearing תפילין tefillin it'll
happen. And it's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara does not distinguish those
cases. It says oh if you've got a problem with that, you
must have a problem with a בעל קרי. baal keri. No, not
a problem with בעל קרי baal keri in the real but that
doesn't happen a while ago. My concern is it's going to happen
while you're wearing the תפילין. tefillin. So it's funny that the גמרא
Gemara doesn't distinguish those cases and rather than feel that it's going
to be
put in a corner to say that a בעל קרי baal keri
has to can never wear תפילין, tefillin, it says the following. So
it says, אמר אביי בילדים ונשותיהם עמהן עסקינן, amar Abaye be-yeladim u-neshoseihem
imahen askinan, no we're not talking about about just being a בעל
קרי. baal keri. We're talking about young men who are married and
they can't go ahead and keep their תפילין tefillin on even if
they're taking, you know, even if they're going to bed just for
a brief
So that's the concern. Now, so therefore, then, even if it's only
like, you know, even if you're only going to bed for a
few minutes, there we're concerned that if you're going to bed with
your wife, you know, with your wife, it'll lead to sex, and
that's the problem. Again, quite fascinating. Number one, so we're not concerned
about that if people aren't so young. They can go to, and
go lie, you know, husband, wife can lie in bed, the man
can be wearing תפילין, tefillin, that's not a problem. Number one. And
number two, again, the fact that the גמרא Gemara felt that it
was the same question about בעל קרי ba'al keri wearing תפילין tefillin
as the concern that actually the person would become a בעל קרי
ba'al keri while wearing תפילין, tefillin, which obviously from the previous גמרא
Gemara seems to be a much more severe concern. Anyway, let's just
wrap this up. תנא רבנן, Tana Rabbanan, שכח ושמש מטתו בתפילין, shachach
v'shimish mitato bitfillin, if somebody forgot and actually had תפילין tefillin on,
again all of this shows you, sort of like the סוכה sukkah
discussion, that it's actually quite fascinating. It just occurs to me, you
know, because it seems to all be a digression from the issue
about about whether you're going to fall asleep. But if you think
about it, there's actually a powerful parallel between how תפילין tefillin used
to be and how סוכה sukkah used to be, as opposed to
how both of those are right now. Right? I was talking about
how סוכה sukkah used to be this very all-encompassing for the whole
week you're living in your סוכה. sukkah. So, it's not like only
during these technical, very narrowly defined experiences. The whole week. So we
give you more latitude because fundamentally you're living in your סוכה. sukkah.
Well, you know what? That's what תפילין tefillin used to be. You'd
wear תפילין tefillin the whole day. So we're reading here discussions about
going and lying in bed with your תפילין tefillin on, you know,
and whatever, and maybe even for people that aren't so young, you
know, they, you know, maybe we think that they're not, you know,
having sex all the time, so they can actually go lie, men
can go lie in bed with their wives with their תפילין tefillin
on, and all these things, and somebody forgets and has sex with
his wife when his תפילין tefillin on. You know, it's like to
us, it's like, it's like scandalous to be even thinking you got
anywhere near those situations. But if you're wearing תפילין tefillin all the
time, right, so then there's going to be like a lot more
latitude of the circumstances in which we let you wear תפילין. tefillin.
You know, and the times... So and so it's again there's a
very interesting, I think it just occurred to me, parallel between what
סוכה sukkah used to be and what תפילין tefillin used to be
as opposed to how we now experience. We now experience very concrete,
very narrowly defined, and we also define, you know, and assume תפילין
tefillin is very narrowly defined, so it never occurred to us that
these situations could even get ever close to these situations when you're
wearing תפילין. tefillin. So let's just finish the situation. שכח ושמש מטתו
בתפילין, shachach v'shimish mitato bitfillin, אינו אוחז לא בקציצה ולא ברצועו. eino
ochez lo biktsitsa velo birtsuo. So
opposed to the case before where a person just had a seminal
emission where he could take off his תפילין tefillin with a, by
holding the straps, here where he actually had sex while he was
wearing תפילין, tefillin, he can't even take it off by the straps.
עד שיטול ידיו ויתלם. ad sheyitol yadav veyitlam. But you have to
first wash your hands, because in the other case we weren't concerned
that his hands were, had touched in improper places, he was just
in an improper state himself. But here that he actually had sex,
his hands touched places that are not clean.
מפני שידיהן עסקניות הן. mipnei sheyadav askaniyot hen. Because hands are very
busy, and therefore even he has to wash his hands before he
even comes in contact with the straps of תפילין. tefillin.
So is he in the bathroom?
What? Yeah, okay, yeah.
Yes, so Texas A&M University Extension Service, the average respiratory rate for
a resting horse is 8 to 16 breaths per minute.
8 to 16 per minute. Ah, there you go.
And when the horse is walking the rate triples. Aha. So but
if you're talking at most seven and a half minutes, and quite
possibly much shorter.
All right. But I'll take seven and a half minutes, it's getting
close to an hour and a half, yeah.
If you could digress, you know, about this whole topic, there'd be
all kinds of modern תפילין tefillin dates.
Right. Oh God, please. Let's not go there.
Though, like,
we suspect I think that for example the תפילין של ראש tefillin
shel rosh were part of like a normal,
normal garment the way the Middle Eastern Arabs like cover their heads
and there's a strap around the top so that would be like
a piece of the, the additional קדושה. kedushah. Right. Do we have
any information about what they did with their hands and their fingers?
In other words if they were wearing the של יד, shel yad,
it's very cumbersome that you can't even go through...
Oh you mean does it go all the way up to the
fingers like ours does? No I don't think that there's, right right
right, I'd have to find out more about that but I, you
know, there's no גמרא Gemara that talks about all the wrappings all
the way up to the hand and it's a very good point.
How do you use your hand if the תפילין tefillin is going
all the way up there?
Or it was much more integrated to the way they...
That's a good point. But I will say that at the same
time it's very clear how regular, how they're wearing תפילין tefillin throughout
the day. There are גמרות Gemaras that speak so heavily about the
constant consciousness that has to be on the תפילין, tefillin, particularly about
the, the תפילין של ראש tefillin shel rosh and always being, always
feeling it and recognizing like the ציץ. tzitz. So it's hard to
imagine anybody could have really lived up to that degree of a
constant consciousness. Yes.
Just thinking about overall this particular סוגיא. sugya. If you look at
at... It's sort of a tension because on the one hand you
know these days we're not doing anything but eating, you know,
and... for or, you know, just really be living in the סוכה.
sukkah. So let's say you have this מקדש Mikdash in your head,
right? Your פסוק posuk for סוכה, sukkah, but it's only—but it's—you're really—you're
not going to be any more comfortable in home or out. So
why not just eat in the סוכה? sukkah?
I agree. I—that—this is what I said yesterday is that I think
that people don't use the פטורים pturim as liberally as they exist
in the גמרא, Gemara, and that's a reflection of the fact that
we don't fundamentally approach the חיוב chiyuv as broadly as we do
in the גמרא. Gemara.
I think yesterday you said
you have a headache, you'd be in? No, technically those things still
apply, but I think the—but I think, you know, as with everything,
the devil's in the details, like how broadly or narrowly do you
understand the circumstances that qualify, and I think even when technically there
is a פטור, ptur, you know, people are not
eager—like—don't take it as readily because of the way in which, you
know, at a religious-psychological level we
have recategorized, you know, redefined the nature of the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay,
so let's now look at the next משנה, Mishnah, which continues this
idea of eating temporarily outside the סוכה. sukkah. מעשה והביאו לו לרבן
יוחנן בן זכאי לטעום את התבשיל. Maase ve-heviu lo le-Rabban Yochanan ben
Zakkai lit'om et hatavshil. They brought for Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai to
taste some of the stew. ולרבן גמליאל שני כותבות ודלי של מים.
u-l'Rabban Gamliel shenei kotevot u-dli shel mayim. They brought to Rabban Gamliel
two pressed dates
and a bucket of water. ואמרו העלום לסוכה, ve-omru ha'alum la-sukkah, and
they said, bring it up to the סוכה. sukkah. Now that's interesting
because those would seem to us to be אכילת עראי, achilat arai,
right? וכשנתנו לו לרבי צדוק, u-keshenatnu lo le-Rabbi Tzadok, when they gave
to Rabbi Tzadok, presumably bread as we'll see, אוכל פחות מכביצה, ochel
pachat mi-kebeitzah,
he would eat less than an egg's worth of bread, נטלו במפה,
netalo be-mappah, he would take it with a handkerchief, ואכלו חוץ לסוכה,
ve-achalo chutz la-sukkah, and
he would eat that amount outside of a סוכה, sukkah, ולא בירך
אחריו, ve-lo berach acharayiv,
and he would not make a—he would not bench because it's less
than a כביצה, kebeitzah, and he wouldn't do נטילת ידים. netilat yadayim.
So a lot of interesting things about Rabbi Tzadok. But let's first
word—about the first two cases. Again, as I mentioned,
what is fascinating is that in סוכה Sukkah more than in a
lot of other מסכתות, masechtot, you have a lot of מעשים, maasim,
you have a lot of actual stories about how the rabbis acted.
It's always quite fascinating, right? Like—like you would think, oh, you know,
everybody's—you know, why not? There's a lot to observe. Yeah, but like
how many stories do you have in מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat, you
know, where everybody's keeping שבת Shabbat every week? So it is interesting
how many stories you have here in סוכה. Sukkah. Okay, מאי למימרא?
Mai l'meimra?
What—so it asks—I just wanted to—to relate to these two together. Because
in one case they brought a cooked food and a bucket of
water in a larger quantity. In the other case he brought a—less
than a כביצה kebeitzah worth of food, and we just learned that
if it's under three you don't have to eat in the סוכה,
sukkah, right, or under
one.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to address the issue of—of quantity. So
let's read the גמרא, Gemara, okay? This will be in the גמרא
Gemara partly, and partly it gets to the issue about what types
of foods, which is not directly discussed in our גמרא. Gemara. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מעשה לסתור? Maase listor? Is this
a story that is—that is coming to contradict? You just said a
temporary eating outside of סוכה, sukkah, and this certainly seems to be—like
to taste—let's start with the first case, which is obviously temporary, right?
It's obviously a small quantity. Have a little bit of a taste
of what's be—of the stew that's cooking. So you just said that
it can be outside of סוכה, sukkah, and here you said they
said, bring it to a סוכה. sukkah. חסורי מחסרא. Chissurei mechasra. Here
it's—it's missing some words, or it's as if it's missing words. והכי
קתני, ve-hachi katani, and this is what it means to say: אם
בא להחמיר על עצמו מחמיר, Im ba l'hachmir al atzmo machmir, if
you want to be strict on yourself, you can be strict, ולית
ביה משום יוהרא, ve-leit bei mishum yuhara, it does not seem to
be like a religious
conceit. And—a better word for יוהרא. yuhara. What word do they usually
translate יוהרא yuhara as? Haughtiness or what—arrogance, religious arrogance. Anyway, okay. ומעשה
נמי והביאו לו לרבן יוחנן בן זכאי לטעום את התבשיל, u-maase nami
ve-heviu lo le-Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai lit'om et hatavshil,
they brought him to taste—taste the stew, ולרבן גמליאל שני כותבות ודלי
של מים, u-l'Rabban Gamliel shenei kotevot u-dli shel mayim, and Rabban Gamliel
they brought two—two dates, ואמרו העלום לסוכה, ve-omru ha'alum la-sukkah, and
they said, bring it to סוכה. sukkah. And this is an idea
we're going to see top of כ"ו עמוד א' Chaf Vav amud
aleph a little bit later as well, that the minimums are minimums,
but there's an idea as we've spoken of of trying to do
everything in a סוכה. sukkah. Now, again, sometimes you do a lot—if
you did a lot more things, sometimes it's not about quantity but
quality, like, you know, you would understand, oh, I have to have
my snack in a סוכה, sukkah, that might actually be a little
bit of like יוהרא. yuhara. You understand why that—why that has to
be a concern, because snacking is not necessarily something that happens, you
know, that happens in the home, right? Whereas some things that are
not technically required might be less of a—you know, more like a
לכתחילה lechatchila rather than just like a בא להחמיר. ba l'hachmir. Like
if I want to be, like, watching TV, reading a novel, sitting
around and שמוזינג schmoozing with people, those are the types of natural
things you do in the home, and that wouldn't even be a
maybe a—להחמיר, l'hachmir, that maybe would be the ideal way to be
מקיים mekayem the סוכה sukkah in this broader sense. But here when
it's just a tiny little snack to be מקפיד makpid to do
it in a סוכה, sukkah, that might be considered a חומרא, chumra,
and the גמרא Gemara says, you know what? Even that is okay
to do.
That's not a יוהרא yuhara concern. One minute. וכשנתנו לו לרבי צדוק,
u-keshenatnu lo le-Rabbi Tzadok,
and when they gave it to Rabbi Tzadok, אוכל פחות מכביצה, ochel
pachat mi-kebeitzah, נטלו במפה. netalo be-mappah. ואכלו חוץ לסוכה ve'achalo chutz lasukkah
ולא בירך אחריו. velo beirach acharov. So now the גמרא Gemara asks
the question that was just asked. הא כביצה בסוכה? Ha kibeitzah basukkah?
It sounds like
he would be saying it's because it's less than a ביצה. beitzah.
It sounds like once it's a ביצה, beitzah, it needs a סוכה.
sukkah. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב יוסף ואביי? Leima tiahavei tiyuvta d'Rav Yosef
v'Abaye? This to be a contradiction of רב יוסף Rav Yosef and
אביי. Abaye. רב יוסף Rav Yosef said up to three eggs doesn't
need a סוכה, sukkah, and even אביי Abaye presumably when he said
like you pop in your mouth that's understood to be one egg's
worth. So according to אביי Abaye even one egg doesn't need a
סוכה. sukkah. And here you only did less than an egg's worth.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, דאפילו פחות מכביצה d'afilu pachos mikibeitzah
because it was less than an egg it got him out of
everything. נטילה וברכה לא בעי. Netilah uvracha lo ba'ei. Less than an
egg not only gets you out of סוכה—סוכה you get out of
even with less than three eggs maybe according to רב יוסף—but Rav
Yosef less than an egg not only got you
out of סוכה, sukkah it got you out of washing your hands
and ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. הא כביצה, Ha kibeitzah, once you have
an egg's worth, בעי נטילה וברכה. ba'ei netilah uvracha. Then you have
to wash your hands and do ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. You might
not need a סוכה sukkah yet, but that, but that, but to
get out of all three it needs to be less than an
egg. So I want to say a few points about this. Number
one, okay the issue about washing hands and ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon.
Obviously, we פסקן pasken ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon you do even with
a כזית. kezayis. That's this huge תוספות Tosafos that we פסקן pasken
even a כזית kezayis for ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. A ברכה ראשונה
bracha rishona you do even wash hands even a ברכה ראשונה bracha
rishona even a tiny amount, okay, because that's you're not allowed to
have pleasure from this world without a ברכה, bracha, so there's no
minimum amount for a ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. But ברכת המזון Birchas
Hamazon we rule is a even a כזית kezayis worth. Handwashing is
actually a debate whether it's a כביצה kibeitzah or כזית, kezayis, what
is the minimum amount for hand washing? And there's some issue about
I didn't re— I have to— I would have to recheck the
exactly the exact debate, the exact positions about it. But there's some
question about whether you make a ברכה bracha if it's between a
כזית kezayis and a כביצה, kibeitzah, how we actually פסקן הלכה למעשה.
pasken halacha l'maaseh. For handwashing? Yeah, but there's some debate about whether
washing hands at the beginning is a כזית kezayis or כביצה הלכה
למעשה. kibeitzah halacha l'maaseh. In terms of the issue about if he
didn't wash his hands why did he why did he cover his
hand? What's this compromise of covering his hand? Sometimes you say oh
there's no water let's just hold it with a napkin. So I'm
not going to discuss that but I will say that, that, רש"י
Rashi says it's just for cleanliness purposes. תוספות Tosafos says no, no,
no, actually he was a כהן Kohen and he would normally eat
any food as if it were תרומה. Terumah. And therefore, sorry, it's
okay, and therefore
even if it weren't the general requirement of washing hands he would
not want to come into direct contact he would not want to
come into direct contact with foods as if it were תרומה Terumah
because if it were תרומה Terumah you couldn't come you would then
even if there was a technical reason to get out of the
handwashing issue you would still have to avoid touching the food. So
there's that's the issue about about covering the hand. From that should
not be inferred that covering the hand's an alternative to washing the
hands. The whole point here is less than a כביצה kibeitzah did
not require washing the hands. So that's as far as those are
concerned. As far as back to the סוכה sukkah, issue, so we
understand a little tasting of the of the תבשיל tavshil is less
than a כביצה. kibeitzah. We understand that this less than a כביצה
kibeitzah maybe even if it was more, it was still we had
the minimums we said before. But the question is how about the
bucket of water? Isn't the bucket of water more than an egg's
worth or two or three eggs' worth? And that gets back to
the point that this גמרא Gemara is not discussing, which is what
type of food are we talking about? Okay, so there is a
discussion in the גמרא Gemara as I said in יומא Yoma about
whether fruit need a סוכה sukkah no matter how much fruit you
eat and the conclusion there seems to be that fruit do not
need a
סוכה. sukkah Presumably water would be obvious that no amount of water
is ever considered קבע. keva. That seems to be my understanding, right,
to answer the question that was just asked. So even so it's
not just an issue of quantity, but the גמרא Gemara here especially
when it gets to the רבי צדוק Rabbi Tzadok case, we were
talking about bread. Because there it was about washing hands and doing
a ברכת המזון. Birchas Hamazon. So there quantity clearly, if quantity matters
at any time, what food definitely needs a סוכה, sukkah it's bread.
And therefore we were looking at that amount of quantity. But some
of the other examples like the bucket of water presumably there was
never an issue that water was not considered קבע keva and would
not need a סוכה. sukkah. Yes?
How does the issue of quantity and under these definitions for requiring
washing and ברכות brachos interact with the distinction between עיקר וטפל? ikkar
v'tafel? Let's say I have a whole a whole plate of salty
herring and an entire פיתה pita to mop it up.
Okay, so I don't want to talk about that, that's a ברכות
brachos discussion. Okay, yes?
What about the ברכה לישב בסוכה? bracha Leishev Basukkah? We haven't talked
about that.
Okay, so that's a good point. That actually comes up there's a
גמרא Gemara that discusses the ברכה. bracha. So and when we get
to that גמרא, Gemara, it's coming up in like a week or
so or more we'll talk about actually I think about two or
three weeks and then we'll talk about that when we get to
it in the גמרא. Gemara. I think it's on דף מ' daf
mem something. Okay, so let's take a look at the משנה. Mishna.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, ארבע עשרה סעודות חייב אדם לאכול
בסוכה. arba esreih seudos chayav adam l'echol basukkah. A person has to
eat 14 meals in a סוכה. sukkah, אחת ביום ואחת בלילה, achas
bayom v'achas balailah, one in the day and one at night,
two meals every day for all seven days. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim,
אין לדבר קצבה, ein ladavar kitzvah, there's no there's no minimum amount
or there's no limit but also no lower limit. חוץ מ... Chutz
mi... The only time you're obligated to eat in the סוכה sukkah.
is the first night. It doesn't mean that you can eat out
of a סוכה. sukkah. We just said it's אסור, assur, you can't
eat out of a סוכה. Sukkah We implicitly said that. Okay, but
the point is you don't have to be eating, right? You don't
have to, you can go on a, you can starve, you can
go on a תענית ta'anis or you can eat fruit or you
can eat things that don't require סוכה. Sukkah. You can always eat
tiny little snacks. Okay, there's not an obligation to make sure that
you eat in a סוכה, Sukkah. you eat an amount that's obligated
in a סוכה Sukkah. except for the first night. ועוד אמר רבי
אליעזר, Ve'od amar Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer also says, מי שלא אכל
ליל יום טוב הראשון ישלים בליל יום טוב האחרון. Mi shelo achal
leil yom tov harishon yashlim bleil yom tov ha'acharon. If somebody did
not eat the first night, he should make up the last night
של חג, shel chag, meaning the night of שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres.
Okay, which is interesting, why is he A, why is he giving
greater status to the first night if he just said that you're
supposed to eat
all fourteen meals and B, how could you be eating שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeres if you're eating it outside of a סוכה? Sukkah, וחכמים
אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the Sages say, we'll talk about that. אין לדבר
תשלומין. Ein ladavar tashlumin. No, I'm sorry, you can't make it up.
ועל זה נאמר מעוות לא יוכל לתקן וחסרון לא יוכל להמנות. Ve'al
zeh ne'emar me'uvas lo yuchal liskon vecheisaron lo yuchal lehimanos. Something perverted
cannot be fixed, right, but Kohelet as the reader took a good
point, and something lacking cannot be made up. Okay, now by the
way, this idea that you can make up until the last night
and the whole idea of תשלומין tashlumin is an idea that is
paralleled in a משנה Mishnah in חגיגה Chagigah that you bring the
חגיגה chagigah on the first day of the חג, chag, but if
you didn't bring the חגיגה chagigah on the first day of חג,
chag, you can bring it on any day of the חג chag
up to and including, right, the last night. So therefore, or the
last day, so whatever, we won't get into details about that. But
anyway, so it's a similar type of a parallel over by there,
but the חכמים Chachamim say that does not work for eating in
the סוכה. Sukkah Okay, so let's see a little גמרא. Gemara. מאי
טעמא דרבי אליעזר? Mai ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer? What's the reasoning of Rabbi
Eliezer that split off the first debate that says you need fourteen
times?
So תשבו, Tishvu, it says you shall dwell in a סוכה, Sukkah?
כעין תדורו, ke'ein taduru, like you live in a house. מה דירה
אחת ביום ואחת בלילה, Mah dirah achas bayom ve'achas balaila, the same
way when you live in a house you eat two meals a
day, אף סוכה אחת ביום ואחת בלילה, af sukkah achas bayom ve'achas
balaila, even in a סוכה Sukkah. you eat two meals a day,
one day, one at night. ורבנן, Verabanan, and the Rabbis would say
back, no, כדירה, kedirah, like you live. מה דירה אי בעי אכיל
אי בעי לא אכיל, Mah dirah ei ba'ei achil ei ba'ei lo
achil, nobody is forcing you to have to eat every day twice
a meal unless you're a kid and your parents are forcing you,
but otherwise you can choose. אף סוכה נמי אי בעי אכיל אי
בעי לא אכיל, Af sukkah nami ei ba'ei achil ei ba'ei lo
achil, even by a סוכה Sukkah, right? Like I've been saying before,
it's not like it's supposed to be a prison, it's not like
it's supposed to demand that you do these types of things. You're
supposed to treat it as you would a house, which gives you
the right to choose and a certain amount of latitude. Okay, so
that's the חכמים. Chachamim. By the way, תוספות Tosafos points out, if
you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תשבו כעין תדורו, tishvu ke'ein taduru, תוספות
בירושלמי יליף בגזירה שוה. Tosafos b'Yerushalmi yalif b'gezeirah shavah. נאמר כאן תשבו
ונאמר להלן פתח אהל מועד תשבו יומם ולילה שבעת ימים. Ne'emar kan
tishvu vene'emar lehalan pesach ohel moed tishvu yomam valaila shivas yamim. מה
שבעת ימים האמורה, Mah shivas yamim ha'amurah, מה ישיבה שנאמר להלן עשה
בה לילות כימים אף כאן עשה בה לילות כימים. mah yeshivah shene'emar
lehalan asah bah leilos k'yamim af kan asah bah leilos k'yamim. Okay,
so meaning that we know of people that dwelt in a place
for seven days, אהרן Aharon and his sons dwelt in the אהל
מועד Ohel Moed for seven days. We're about to read it, and
therefore if you live in a סוכה, Sukkah you gotta live constantly
seven days. So that's interesting, learning it out from the אהל מועד
Ohel Moed idea and that idea of what it means to fully
inhabit a place, but also we've been discussing before סוכות Sukkos ענני
כבוד ananei kavod and being in the presence of God and sort
of being
under directly in God's presence or the whole idea of the קודש
קדשים Kodesh Kadashim and the כפורת kapores and the כרובים, keruvim, you
might remember all of that imagery. So here there's one connection of
Rabbi Eliezer that's putting you in the אהל מועד Ohel Moed like
with אהרן Aharon and his sons. So very powerful. But our גמרא
Gemara focuses more on what it really means to fully live in
a place. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי הכי, Ei
hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, אפילו ליל יום טוב
ראשון נמי? afilu leil yom tov rishon nami? If it's totally at
your option whether you're going to eat or not, when you eat
it has to be in a סוכה, Sukkah but you can choose
whether to eat or not, so even on the first night? אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi
Shimon ben Yehotzadak, נאמר כאן חמשה עשר, ne'emar kan chamishah asar, it
says on the fifteenth of the seventh month of תשרי, Tishrei, ונאמר
חמשה עשר בחג המצות, vene'emar chamishah asar bechag hamatzos,
and it says on the fifteenth of the first month by חג
המצות. chag hamatzos. מה להלן לילה הראשון חובה, Mah lehalan laila harishon
chovah,
the same way the first night there's an obligation to eat מצה,
matzah, מכאן
ואילך רשות, mikan va'eilach reshus, from there on after you can choose
to eat מצה. matzah. But we understand that although the תורה Torah
says seven days you shall eat מצה, matzah, that is not strictly
mandated. The way we know that is because in one place the
תורה Torah says six days eat מצה, matzah, so we understand that
that's to signify or signal that it's not an obligation to eat
each day, but that the nature of the חג chag is a
time when מצה matzah is eaten, but you don't actually strictly have
to eat it every day. There only the first night is an
obligation. So here too מכאן ואילך רשות, mikan va'eilach reshus, אף כאן
לילה הראשון חובה. af kan laila harishon chovah. Here too only the
first night is an obligation. מכאן ואילך רשות. Mikan va'eilach reshus. Thereon
after it is volitional. Now it's not the same volitional because you
can actually never eat מצה matzah for the rest of פסח, Pesach,
but by סוכות Sukkos when you eat are eating you must eat
in a סוכה, Sukkah, but nevertheless it is possible to go the
whole חג chag without eating in a סוכה Sukkah, if you just
never eat the requisite amount. So similarly there you can you can
choose never to eat מצות matzos other than the first night.
You just said that we don't have to eat in the סוכה
sukkah, if we eat certain foods.
Right, so that's what I said. You can choose to eat the
types and the amounts right. I should have said it's no
obligation then to eat in the סוכה? sukkah Correct, after the first
night?
Correct, correct. All I'm saying is that the difference is is that
you in during סוכות Sukkos you can put yourself in circumstances that
create an obligation. When you are eating let's say a certain amount
and a certain type of food you become obligated in a סוכה,
sukkah whereas by מצה matzah that never happens. So for example, if
I eat מצה matzah if I eat מצה matzah if I eat
מצה matzah on the other days of פסח Pesach I don't make
a ברכה. bracha. When I eat in a סוכה sukkah? on the
other days of סוכות Sukkos I do make a ברכה. bracha. And
the basic difference is is that by סוכה sukkah, when you are
choosing to have bread and to have a certain amount, then you
actually become obligated, whereas by מצה matzah you never become obligated after
the first night. But in both cases you can you can construct
it that you'll never have to eat on the rest of the
days. Okay, מה להלן לילה ראשון חובה אף כאן לילה ראשון חובה.
ma lehalan layla rishon chova af kan layla rishon chova. Okay. ואף
כאן לילה ראשון חובה מכאן ואילך רשות. ve'af kan layla rishon chova
mikan va'eylakh reshut. והתם מנלן, vehasam minalan, where do you know the
first night is an obligation? אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says
בערב תאכלו מצות. ba'erev tokhlu matzos. Now actually the verse says בחמשה
עשר בחדש בערב עד יום
האחד ועשרים לחדש בערב תאכלו
מצות. bachamishah asar bachodesh ba'erev ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev tokhlu
matzos.
So actually the whole verse in context says eat מצות matzos for
seven days, but we cut out those three words to read nighttime
eat מצות, matzos, meaning only the first night is there an obligation.
הכתוב קבעו חובה, hakatuv kevao chova,
the verse made it an obligation. So the same way it's an
obligation the first night for פסח, Pesach, it's an obligation the first
night for סוכות Sukkos regardless of you don't get to choose whether
you want to have a meal or not. Now there's a lot
of interesting things that come from this גמרא, Gemara, I'll just mention
a few of them briefly. Number one, תוספות Tosafos points out it
sounds like you can choose not to have a meal on the
other days of on the rest of חול המועד Chol HaMoed and
even on the daytime of סוכות. Sukkos. Okay, but wait a minute.
תוספות Tosafos says, oh that too, תוספות Tosafos says but does that
mean that you don't have a חיוב chiyuv to have a סעודה
seudah on the other you know you know on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? Because like the daytime of סוכות Sukkos you don't have to
have a סעודה, seudah, so if I forget A, I wouldn't have
to have a סעודה seudah and B, if I forget let's say
יעלה ויבא Ya'aleh VeYavo in benching, I wouldn't have to say it
again because you only have to say it again when there's an
obligation to have a סעודה. seudah. So תוספות Tosafos thinks yeah, that
actually does sound like that's the conclusion of this גמרא, Gemara, that
only that there's no חיוב chiyuv of סעודה. seudah. You know, now
of course you can make a distinction again, well maybe you have
to eat a כזית kezayis but you don't have to eat a
כביצה. kibeitzah. There's that gap between what technically makes a סעודה seudah
and what degree is obligated in a סוכה. sukkah Okay, but that's
one issue תוספות Tosafos raises is that really true you don't have
to have a סעודה seudah on the on the other days and
certainly not on the rest of יום טוב? Yom Tov? Right, wouldn't
you think you would have an obligation of יום טוב Yom Tov
day? That's, I don't know, that's one question. The other question is
more directly about the מצוה mitzvah of eating in a סוכה sukkah
is how much is the eating of a סוכה sukkah. on the
first night like eating of מצה? matzah? The big debate that comes
up in the ראשונים Rishonim is to what degree is it in
the context of
אכילת סוכה achilas sukkah or living in a סוכה, sukkah an expression
of living in a סוכה, sukkah and to what degree is it
more like אכילת מצה achilas matzah and it just focuses on do
this eating, not in the context of living in a סוכה? sukkah,
What's the biggest נפקא מינא? nafka mina? The biggest נפקא מינא nafka
mina is let's say circum- well A, there's a שיעור shiur question,
I'll get to you. But B, let's say it's circumstances that would
not constitute דירת סוכה. diras sukkah. Let's say you're מצטער, mitzta'er, let's
say you're a חולה, choleh, let's say it's raining. Do you still
have to eat in the סוכה? sukkah, If it's just a way
of doing the מצוה mitzvah of דירת סוכה diras sukkah but must
be done on the first night with eating, but if it's not
דירה dira because it's raining and because I'm מצטער mitzta'er and חולה
choleh and all of those, maybe I'm exempt. Or no, maybe tough
luck. The first night it's a מצוה, mitzvah, eat כזית kezayis in
the סוכה sukkah? regardless of whether it normally constitutes דירת סוכה. diras
sukkah. So that is a big debate what happens when it rains
the first night, when people are waiting is it going to stop
raining before חצות, chatzos, after חצות, chatzos, when can you actually go
to bed and just decide it's not just go ahead with your
meal. So that is a big מחלוקת ראשונים. machlokes Rishonim. Relatedly, as
Michael says, how much? If it's about learning straight from מצה matzah
and not about a form of דירת סוכה, diras sukkah, so maybe
I'm יוצא yotzei with כזית. kezayis. If however it's a way of
doing the normal דירת סוכה diras sukkah but must be done the
first night, maybe it needs a כביצה, kibeitzah, right? So that's or
more than a כביצה, kibeitzah, whatever the amount is. תוספות, Tosafos, if
you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos actually quotes a ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
תוספות Tosafos תשבו כעין תדורו. teshvu ke'ein taduru. Look at the last
few lines of תוספות, Tosafos, he says like this. He says
חביריא בעון, chavrayia ba'on, it's like four five lines before the תוספות
Tosafos ends of תשבו. teshvu. מה להלן עד שיכנס למצה כשהוא תאווה
אף כאן עד שיכנס לסוכה בתאווה. ma lehalan ad sheyikanes lematzah keshehu
ta'avah af kan ad sheyikanes lesukkah beta'avah. If we're learning it out
from מצה matzah maybe we should say the same way you're not
supposed to eat before it gets to be close to nightfall so
you eat מצות matzos with an appetite, maybe here too. Now again,
if you think about it סוכה sukkah? is not about an appetite-
for the food, the eating is just an expression of what it
means to be living in a place, but maybe for the first
night it does become focused on the food that you're eating and
you have to have an appetite for that food. It does become
like the מצוה mitzvah of eating מצה. matzah. Or he says another
thing, רב זירא בעי, Rav Zeira bayei, אימא להלן עד שיאכל כזית
דגן מצה אף כאן עד שיאכל כזית דגן בסוכה. Ima lehallan ad
sheyochal kezayit dagan matzah af kan ad sheyochal kezayit dagan basuccah.
Now there the question might be as Michael says, it's a כזית
kezayit as opposed to a כביצה, kebeitzah, but also maybe it's an
issue about bread, right? The same way מצה matzah has to be
made out of bread, maybe you're יוצא סוכה yotzei succah without it
being bread? Maybe you're יוצא סוכה yotzei succah with מזונות, mezonot, maybe
you're יוצא סוכה yotzei succah with meat and potatoes? But no, maybe
if we learn it out from מצה matzah it has to דוקא
davka be bread. So this becomes a lot of interesting implications of
how much is it mapped just like מצה. matzah. Eat bread in
a סוכה, sukkah כזית kezayit worth? Or how much is it, no,
the first night, the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה sukkah has to be
done the first night in the context of what it means to
do the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה. succah, So there's a very lot
of debate of the ראשונים rishonim around those issues. And then let's
not forget the other point about the idea of the rest of
the time when you dwell, you dwell in a סוכה, succah but
you have more latitude about what's to be doing that would require
it or not require it. Let's now continue with the next statement
of ר' אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. ועוד אמר רבי אליעזר. V'od amar Rebbi
Eliezer. So Rebbi Eliezer also says if you miss the first night
you can make up until the last night. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא אמר ר' אליעזר ארבע עשרה סעודות חייב אדם לאכול בסוכה
אחת ביום ואחת בלילה. Veha amar Rebbi Eliezer arba esrei seudot chayav
adam leechol basuccah achat bayom v'achat balailah. One minute, doesn't he say
fourteen meals? Now what exactly is the question about the fact that
he says fourteen meals? Why does that seem to be in contradiction
to the idea that he says that you make it up the
last night? So רש"י, Rashi, one way of understanding the way רש"י
Rashi explains it, but there's a couple of ways to understand it.
One is why is he emphasizing if you miss the first night?
Meaning if he says you have to make up fourteen meals, then
he should say if you miss anyone. What's the emphasis of the
first night? Or another sort of way nuance way of saying it
is, if he just said focus on the fact that you had
a מצוה mitzvah the first night, then I could understand that you
make it up on the last night because then it doesn't emphasize
סוכה. succah. Like it's not, there's a מצוה mitzvah to eat the
first night. You miss the first night, fine, you do it any
other night, you do it even the last night, it's about eating,
some you're making up some eating which happened to be in a
סוכה. succah, But if you're saying no, a מצוה mitzvah of סוכה
succah. demands fourteen meals, then how could you make up a סוכה
succah. problem after סוכות? Succos? How good is it to do it
after סוכות? Succos? So what's going on here? So two certain ways
to understand the question of ר' אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. Let's see what
the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is. אמר רב בירא אמר רב אמי חזר
בו רבי אליעזר. Amar Rav Bira amar Rav Ami chazar bo Rebbi
Eliezer.
Rebbi Eliezer reversed himself. Now which one did he reverse himself from?
This is a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות. Tosafot. רש"י Rashi
says he dropped the idea of fourteen. He basically went back to
the rabbis and said only the first night is what really matters.
But once it's about the first night, it doesn't have to be
focused particularly on סוכה. succah There's a מצוה mitzvah of eating the
first night that actually connects to the discussion we had a minute
ago. And therefore if you miss the first night, you make it
up any other night and even up to the last night even
if you're not eating in a סוכה. succah That's the way רש"י
Rashi explained it. תוספות Tosafot says no no no, it's the other
thing he reversed himself from. It's what he said fourteen, basically according
to תוספות Tosafot there's an idea of fourteen meals, but don't necessarily
double underline the word סוכה. succah. There's an idea of fourteen meals
during the חג. chag. Okay, but it's not so much about סוכה
succah. have to be fourteen meals. And therefore if you missed one
of those meals, not even necessarily the first one, then you can
actually make it up even on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret because it's
about fourteen meals, it's not necessarily fourteen meals בסוכה. basuccah. Now why
did he say לילי יום טוב הראשון? leilei Yom Tov harishon? So
actually this, that גרסא girsa is a late גרסא. girsa. The מהרש"א
Maharsha says all the earlier משניות Mishnayot said מי שלא אכל יום
טוב הראשון, mi shelo achal Yom Tov harishon, not לילי יום טוב
הראשון. leilei Yom Tov harishon. And it's not about the first night.
He says חדשים מקרוב באו. chadashim mikarov bau. Now there's these new
גרסאות, girsaot, these you know that say לילי יום טוב הראשון leilei
Yom Tov harishon in order to make it connect to what the
rabbis said. But the actual original גרסא girsa he says no, you
missed one of the days and therefore you make it up. יום
טוב, Yom Tov, יום טוב Yom Tov can be you know, you...
right. But once you're not saying ליל יום טוב leil Yom Tov
then it could also be less לאו דוקא. lav davka. Okay. So
there's an interesting debate now, right, of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
whether he is saying making up the first night, which is what
רש"י Rashi said, and he's dropping the idea of fourteen, or whether
he's saying make up any missed night, but it's not necessarily focused
on the סוכה succah. per se.
Wait, on according to תוספות Tosafot
on the fact that it's about fourteen in a סוכה, succah that
סוכה succah is central? No, he's not חוזר chozer on fourteen. He
needs fourteen. He's חוזר chozer on the idea that it's central to
the idea of סוכה. succah, Because you need fourteen meals over יום
טוב, Yom Tov, but not because בסוכה. basuccah. And therefore you can
make up one of those meals even afterwards, even on שמיני עצרת.
Shemini Atzeret.
So if I missed three, do I have to eat... so presumably
not, presumably he lets you make up one. Again, there's also a
question how much implicitly we're comparing it to the חגיגה, chagigah, which
it does parallel to in some ways by the language, and you
make it up even on the eighth day and so on, and
how much that's only one thing to make up. Let's take a
look. It's a good question how many can you. Let's take a
look, let's get at least to the bottom of the דף. daf.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. משלימין במה? Mashlimin bamah? What
what do you do... make up the missed one for? אילימא בריפתא
*I-leima be-rifta*, if it's bread, סעודת דיומא קאכיל *se'udat de-yoma ka-akhil*, that's
the normal meal you would be having, let's say you're eating it
on שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*, you know, so, what makes that to
be distinct? What makes that count as the makeup? Okay, so maybe
you could say the fact that you're doing two is like when
you make up a missed דאוונען *davening*, you know, the fact that
you did a second one. But that's, according to that, there's nothing
distinctive about that. So that won't be good for a makeup. אלא
מאי *Ela mai*? ישלים במיני תרגימא *Yashlim be-minei targima*. You do it
with various delicacies. Now, what are these delicacies? So if you look
at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says מיני תרגימא *minei targima*, לאחר
שסילק יביא פרפרות ומעדנים לפניו כגון פירות וקטנית וקליות ומבושלות *le-achar she-silek
yavi parpara'ot u-ma'adanim lefanav kegon perot ve-katnit ve-kalotot u-mevushalot*. So various cooked
dishes. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* also throws in fruit. תוספות *Tosafot* says, no,
excuse me, if you're making it up and what you're making up
is an אכילה בסוכה *achila be-sukkah*, then it has to be the
type of eating that would require a סוכה succah *sukkah*. And תוספות
*Tosafot* goes back to remind us that fruit doesn't require a סוכה
succah. *sukkah*. So according to תוספות *Tosafot*, מיני תרגימא *minei targima* are
things like meat and potatoes that do require a סוכה sukka. *sukkah*.
Okay, but this again gets to that issue of: are there things
that are not bread and not מזונות *mezonot* that require a סוכה
sukka *sukkah*? And for תוספות *Tosafot*, the answer is yes, and that's
the מיני תרגימא *minei targima*. But the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is not
clear about that. Again, since the גמרא *Gemara* is allowing you to
do a makeup even on שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*, maybe it doesn't
have to be things that are חייב *chayav* in a סוכה sukka
*sukkah*, but תוספות *Tosafot* assumes that it does. One minute. So yeah,
let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi*, we taught
similarly, אם השלים במיני תרגימא יצא *im hishlim be-minei targima yatza*. If
you did your makeup with מיני תרגימא *minei targima*, then you are,
then that counts as your makeup for, for, what do you call
it,
for the missed meal. Now רש"י *Rashi* says, he says: if you
did your makeup with מיני תרגימא *minei targima*, suggest that if you
actually had a real bread meal, it would certainly be a makeup,
which is a little bit different than the גמרא *Gemara* before, because
the גמרא *Gemara* before made it sound like it had to be
ניכר *nikar* as being distinct. Here, תניא *tanya*, it's okay to make
it up with מיני תרגימא *minei targima*.
I'll read רש"י *Rashi* again.
I know. So I'm saying that the גמרא *Gemara* before made it
sound like that wouldn't be good. Here the language אם השלים *im
hishlim* sounds like that certainly would be good, and that's what רש"י
*Rashi* says: וכל שכן אם קבע סעודה שנייה בלחם ובשר *ve-chol she-ken
im kava se'uda sheniya be-lechem u-vasar*, says רש"י *Rashi*. Okay, so
but again, before the גמרא *Gemara* sounded like it had to be
distinct. I don't know. I don't know.
Okay, one minute.
Okay, so גמרא *Gemara* says like this. So shall, let's get a
little bit further to the bottom. שאל אפוטרופוס של אגריפס המלך *Sha'al
apotropas shel Agrippas ha-melech*. So the sort of the whatever, the manager
of Agrippas the king asked את רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer *et Rabbi
Eliezer*: כגון אני *kegon ani*, like I say, שאיני רגיל לאכול אלא
סעודה אחת ביום *she-eini ragil le-echol ela se'uda achat be-yom*, I only
have one meal a day and you, רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, say
that on סוכות sukkos, *Sukkot* we have to have two meals each
day. So this is again תוספות'ס *Tosafot's* proof that רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* didn't reverse himself about the idea of 14 meals. מהו שאוכל
סעודה אחת ואפטר *mahu she-ochal se'uda achat ve-ipater*? Maybe I'll just have
one meal in my סוכה sukka. *sukkah* and be done with it?
אמר לו *Amar lo*, he said back to him: בכל יום ויום
אתה ממשיך כמה פרפרות לכבוד עצמך *be-chol yom va-yom ata mamshich kama
parpara'ot lichvod atzmecha*, every day you have for yourself a lot of
delicacies to, for your own respect, you know, to indulge yourself. ועכשיו
אי אתה ממשיך פרפרת אחת לכבוד קונך *ve-achshav i ata mamshich parparet
achat lichvod konecha*? You can't have one one little delicacy in honor
to honor your creator? But what's interesting about this is A, the
idea that you needed more than one meal a day, or, you
know, whatever, you needed a regular two meals a day, and B,
the idea of פרפרת *parparet*, a delicacy, connects to what we said
before about the מיני תרגימא *minei targima*, that some of those 14
can't possibly be made up even without a strict סעודה *se'uda*. Maybe
one way to get to the number 14 is to allow yourself
to do some of these some of these פרפראות *parpara'ot* or what
the גמרא *Gemara* called before מיני תרגימא *minei targima*. Let's read one
more story. ועוד שאלו *Ve-od sha'alo*, he asked him as well: כגון
אני שיש לי שתי נשים *kegon ani she-yesh li shtei nashim*, I
have two wives, אחת בטבריה ואחת בציפורי *achat bi-Tverya ve-achat be-Tzipori*, one
in Tiberias and one in Sepphoris, ויש לי שתי סוכות אחת בטבריה
ואחת בציפורי *ve-yesh li shtei sukkot achat bi-Tverya ve-achat be-Tzipori*, and I
have two sukkot, one in Tiberias and one in Sepphoris. מהו שאצא
מסוכה לסוכה ואפטר *mahu she-etzei mi-sukkah le-sukkah ve-ipater*? Can I go from
one sukkah to the next? It's funny to use an exempting. What's
the exempting? But okay. Can I go, he have one day in
one sukkah the next day in the next? אמר לו *Amar lo*:
לא *lo*. I'm sorry, no. שאני אומר *She-ani omer*, because my position
is: כל היוצא מסוכה לסוכה ביטל מצותה של ראשונה *kol ha-yotzei mi-sukkah
le-sukkah biteil mitzvata shel rishona*. When you leave one sukkah because, notice,
right, he said you have to have 14 meals in a sukkah.
So that is not just about me personally I have to have
14 meals, but what makes the sukkah—we're going to read one
more one more sentence—what makes the sukkah a house is that you
be using it for all seven days. So if you split that
between two סוכות *sukkot*, neither sukkah gets to be defined as your
house, you've been dwelling regularly. But the idea is that the סוכה
sukka *sukkah* has to be your בית *bayit* and that has to
be in one sukkah. תניא *Tanya*, we turn in a בריתא *Beraita*:
רבי אליעזר אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*: אין יוצאין מסוכה לסוכה *ein yotzin
mi-sukkah le-sukkah*. You cannot leave one sukkah and eat in another sukkah.
Your 14 meals all have to be in the same sukkah, seven
days in the same sukkah. ואין עושין סוכה בחולו של מועד *ve-ein
osin sukkah be-cholo shel mo'ed*. And similarly, you can't make a sukkah
in the middle of a חג *chag*, because in order for it
to be a sukkah, it has to be. to be for all
seven days the same סוכה. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the sages
disagree, יוצאין מסוכה לסוכה ועושין סוכה בחול המועד, yotzin misukka lesukka v'oisin
sukka b'chol hamoed, you can do it. They also say you don't
need fourteen meals. It doesn't have to be for the whole seven
days. ושוין, v'shavin, but they agree שנפלה שחוזר ובונה בחול המועד. shenofla
shechozer ubona b'chol hamoed. If it did fall down, you can rebuild
it. That would be considered to be a continuation of the same
סוכה. And this gets to the whole interesting discussion what we've had
before in the גמרא, that old Greek-ish question, I forget what it's
called, about you know, the ship that you're constantly replacing one board
at a time, is it the same ship or not? So your
סוכה falls down and you rebuild it, is it the same סוכה
or not? תוספות indicates that you'd have to use the same wood
to rebuild it for רבי אליעזר to be considered the same סוכה.
רש"י sounds a little bit more like since it fell down, anything
you build is considered a conceptual substitute even if it's in a
different place and it's different wood. But nevertheless, this is רבי אליעזר'ס
Rebbe Eliezer's idea that it's not just your personal obligation to eat
two meals a day for seven days, but what makes it your
סוכה is that you've been living in it constantly for those whole
seven days, and if you don't do that and you split it
between two סוכות, you're not
יוצא.
yotzei.